<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties answer, to a printed book, intituled, A remonstrance, or the declaration of the Lords and Commons now assembled in Parliament, 26. May 1642 In answer to a declaration under His Majesties name, concerning the business of Hull.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78637</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229539</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895305</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895305</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152625</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78637)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152625)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2310:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties answer, to a printed book, intituled, A remonstrance, or the declaration of the Lords and Commons now assembled in Parliament, 26. May 1642 In answer to a declaration under His Majesties name, concerning the business of Hull.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at York: and re-printed at London for William Ley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament. --  Proceedings. 1642-05-26 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hull (England) --  History, Military --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152625:1"/>
            <p>HIS MAJESTIES ANSWER, To a Printed Book, INTITULED, A REMONSTRANCE, OR THE Declaration of the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, 26. May 1642:</p>
            <p>In anſwer to a Declaration under His Majeſties Name, concerning the buſineſſe of HULL.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>York:</hi> And Re-printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>William Ley,</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152625:2"/>
            <head>His Majeſties Anſwer to a printed Book, intituled, <hi>A Remonſtrance, or the Declaration of the Lords and Commons now aſſembled in Parliament, the</hi> 26. <hi>of May,</hi> 1642. In Anſwer to a Declaration under His Majeſties Name, concerning the buſineſſe of <hi>Hull.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THough whoſoever looks over the late Remonſtrance, intituled, <hi>A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Lords and Commons, of the</hi> 26. <hi>of May,</hi> will not think We have much reaſon to be pleaſed with it; yet We cannot but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the plain dealing and ingenuity of the Framers and Contrivers of that Declaration (which hath been wrought in a hotter and quicker Forge then any of the reſt) who would no longer ſuffer Us to be affronted, by being told, <hi>They would make Vs a great and glorious King,</hi> whileſt they uſed all poſſible skill to reduce Us to extreame Want and Indigency; and that <hi>They would make Vs to be loved at home and feared abroad,</hi> whileſt they endeavoured by all poſſible wayes, to render Us odious to Our good Subjects, and contemptible to all forreign Princes; but, like Round-dealing men, tell Us in plain Engliſh, That they have done Us no wrong, becauſe We are not capable of receiving any; and That they have taken nothing from Us, becauſe Wee had never any thing of Our owne to loſe: If this Doctrine be true, and that indeed We ought to be of no other conſideration, then they have informed Our people in that Declaration; that Gentleman is much more excuſable, that ſaid publikely (unreproved) <hi>That the happineſſe of this Kingdome doth not depend on Vs, or upon any of the Royall Branches of that Root;</hi> And the other, who ſaid, <hi>We were not worthy to be King of England:</hi> Language very monſtrous to be allowed by either Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of which, by the help of God and the Law, We muſt have ſome Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. But We doubt not, all Our good Subjects do now plainly diſcern, through the Mask and Viſard of their hipocriſie, what their Deſigne is, and will no more look upon the Framers and Contrivers of that Declaration, as upon both Houſes of Parliament (whoſe freedom and juſt Priviledges Wee will alwaies maintain, and in whoſe behalf We are as much ſlandered as for Our Self) but as a Faction of Malignant, Schiſmaticall, and Ambitious Perſons, whoſe deſigne is, and alwaies hath been, to alter the whole frame of Government both of Church and State, and to ſubject both King and People to their own Lawleſſe, Arbitrary power and Government; of whoſe Perſons, and of whoſe Deſigne, We ſhall, within a very ſhort time, give Out good Subjects, and the world a full, and (We hope) a ſatisfactory Narration.</p>
            <p>The Contrivers and Penners of that Declaration (of whom We would be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood to ſpeak, when Wee mention any of their undutifull acts againſt Us) tell you, <hi>That the great Affaires of this Kingdom, and the miſerable and blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding condition of the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland, <hi>will afford them little leiſure to ſpend their time in Declarations, Anſwers and Replies;</hi> Indeed, the miſerable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable condition of both Kingdoms would require ſomewhat elſe at their hands: But We would gladly know, how they have ſpent their time ſince their Receſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152625:2"/>(now almoſt eight moneths) but in Declarations Remonſtrances and Invectives againſt Vs and Our Government, or in preparing matter for them: Have We in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited them to any ſuch expence of time, by beginning Arguments of that nature: Their leiſure, or their Inclination is not as they pretend: And what is their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Publiſhing their Petitions to Vs, their Declarations and Remonſtrances of Us, their odious Votes, and Reſolutions, ſometimes of one, ſometimes of both Houſes, againſt Us (never in this manner communicated before this Parliament) but an Appeale to the People? And, in Gods Name, let them judge of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they have truſted,</p>
            <p>Their firſt Quarrell is (as it is alwayes, to let them into their franck Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Vs and Our Actions) againſt the <hi>Malignant Party,</hi> whom they are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſtil to call, and never to prove, to be Our evill Counſellors; but indeed, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more evident by their whole Proceedings, then that by the <hi>Malignant Party,</hi> they intend all the Members of both Houſes, who agree not with them in their Opinion (hence have come their diſtinction of good and bad Lords, of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ill affected of the Houſe of Commons, who have bin proſcribed, and their Names Liſted and read in Tumults) and all the Perſons of the Kingdome, who approve not of their actions; So that if, in truth, they would be ingenuous, and name the Perſons they intend, who would be the Men (upon whom that Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Malignity would be caſt) but they, who have ſtood ſtoutly and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably for the Religion, the Liberties, the Lawes, for all publike Intereſts (ſo long as there was any to be ſtood for) they, who have alwayes beene, and are as zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Profeſſors, and (ſome of them) as able and earneſt Defendors of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctrine againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as any are; who have often and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beſought Vs to conſent, that no Indifferent and Vnneceſſary Ceremony might be preſſed upon weake and tender Conſciences, and that Wee would agree to a Bill for that purpoſe; they, to whoſe Wiſdome, Courage, and Councell, the Kingdome oweth as much, as it can to ſubjects; and upon whoſe unblemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Lives, Envy it ſelfe can lay no Imputation, nor endeavoured to lay any, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their Vertues brought them to Our Knowledge and Favour. Let the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of this Declaration be faithfull to themſelves, and conſider all thoſe Perſons of both Houſes, whom they, in their Conſciences, know to diſſent from them in the Matter and Language of that Declaration, and in all thoſe undutifull actions, of which we complaine: and will they not be found in Honour, Fortune, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Reputation, and Weight (if not in number) much Superiour to them? So much for the Evill Councellors: Now, what is the Evill Councell it ſelfe? Our comming from <hi>London,</hi> (where We, and many, whoſe affections to Vs are very eminent, were in danger every day to be torne in peices) to <hi>Yorke,</hi> where We, and all ſuch who will put themſelves under Our Protection, may live (Wee thanke God, and the loyalty and affection of this good people) very ſecurely; Our not ſubmitting Our Selfe abſolutely (and renouncing Our owne Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) to the Votes and Reſolutions of the Contrivers of that Declaration, when they tell Vs, They are above Vs, and may (by our owne Authority) doe with Vs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152625:3"/>what they pleaſe; and Our not being contented, that all Our good ſubjects Lives and Fortunes ſhall be diſpoſed of by their Votes, but by the knowne Law of the land: This is the evill Councell given and taken: And will not all Men beleeve there needs much power and skil (of the <hi>Malignant Party</hi>) to infuſe this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell into Vs? And now apply the Argument, the Contrivers of that Declaration makes for themſelves: Is it probable, or poſſible, that ſuch men whom We haue mentioned (who muſt have ſo great a ſhare in the miſery) ſhould take ſuch pains in the procuring thereof, and ſpend ſo much time, and run ſo many hazards, to make themſelves Slaves, and to ruine the Freedome of this Nation? We ſay, with a clear and upright Conſcience to God Almighty, Whoſoever harbours the leaſt thought in his breaſt of ruining or violating the publike Liberty or Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Kingdome, or the juſt Freedome and Priviledge of Parliament, let him be accurſed; and hee ſhall be no Councellour of Ours that will not ſay, Amen. For the contrivers of that declaration, We have not ſaid any thing which might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply any inclination in them to be Slaves; that which Wee have charged them, is with invading the publike Liberty, and Our Preſumption may be very ſtrong and vehement, that (though they have no mind to bee Slaves) they are not unwilling to bee Tyrants: (What is Tyrannie, but to admit no Rule to governe by, but their owne wils?) And We know the miſery of <hi>Athens</hi> was at the higheſt, when it ſuffered under the thirty Tyrants.</p>
            <p>If that Declaration had told Vs (as indeed it might, and as in Iuſtice it ought to have done) that the Preſidents of any of our Anceſtors did fall ſhort and much below what hath beene done by Vs this Parliament, in point of Grace and Favour to Our People, Wee ſhould no otherwiſe have wondred at it, then at ſuch a truth, in ſuch a place: But when (to juſtifie their having done more then ever their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors did) it tels Our good Subjects (as moſt injuriouſly moſt inſolently it doth) <hi>That the higheſt and moſt unwarrantable Preſidents of any of Our Predeceſſors doe fall ſhort, and much below what hath beene done to them this Parliament by Vs,</hi> Wee muſt confeſſe Our ſelfe amazed, and not able to underſtand them: And We muſt tel thoſe ungratefull Men (who dare tell their King, That they may, without want of Modeſty and Duty, depoſe him) That the condition of Our Subjects, when (by whatſoever Accidents and Conjunctures of time) it was at worſt, under Our power, unto which (by no default of Ours) they ſhall be ever againe reduced, was, by many degrees, more pleaſant and happy, then that to which their furious pretence of Reformation hath brought them: Neither are we afraid of the higheſt Preſidents of other Parliaments, which theſe men boldly (Our good ſubjects will call it worſe) tell Vs, They might without want of Modeſty and Duty, make their Patterns: If We had no other ſecurity againſt thoſe Preſidents, but their Modeſty and Duty, Wee were in a miſerable condition, as all perſons will bee who depend upon them.</p>
            <p>That Declaration will not allow Our Inference, That by avowing the Act of Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham,</hi> they doe deſtroy the Title and Intereſt of all Our Subjects to their Lands and Goods; but confeſſeth, if they were found guilty of that charge,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152625:3"/>it were indeed a very great crime. And doe they not in this Declaration, admit themſelves guilty of this very Crime? Doe they not ſay, <hi>Who doubts but that a Parliament may diſpoſe of any thing, wherein VVee, or Our Subjects have a Right in ſuch a way as that the Kingdome may not be in danger thereby?</hi> Doe they not then call themſelves This Parliament, and challenge this Power without Our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? Doe they not extend this Power to all Caſes, where the neceſſity, or the common good of the Kingdome is concerned? and doe they not arrogate unto themſelves alone the judgement of this Danger, this Neceſſity, this Common Good of the Kingdome? What is, if this be not to unſettle the Security of all mens Eſtates, and to expoſe them to an arbitrary Power of their owne? If a Faction ſhall at any time, by Cunning, or Force, or abſence, or accident, prevaile over a major part of both Houſes, and pretend that they are Evill Councellors, a <hi>Malignant Party</hi> about the King, by whom the Liberty and Religion of the Kingdome are both in danger; This they may doe: they have done it. Then they may take away (be it from the King or People) whatſoever they, in their judgements, ſhall thinke fit: This is lawfull, they have declared it ſo. Let the world judge, whether We charge them unjuſtly, and whether they are not guilty of the Crime, which themſelves confeſſe (being proved) is a great one, and how ſafely We might commit the Power, theſe people deſire into their hands, who, in all probability, would be no ſooner poſſeſſed of it, then they would revive that Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die which Maſter <hi>Hooker</hi> relates of the Anabaptiſts in <hi>Germany,</hi> who talking of nothing but Faith, and of the true Feare of God, and that Riches and Honour were vanity; at firſt, upon the great Opinion of their Humility, Zeal, and Devotion, procured much Reverence and Eſtimation with the people. After finding how many perſons they had enſnared with their Hypocriſie, they began to propoſe to themſelves, to reforme both the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill Government of the State; Then, becauſe, poſſibly, they might meet with ſome Oppoſition, they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly entred into a League of Aſſociation; and ſhortly after (finding the power they had gotten with the credulous People) enriched themſelves with all kind of ſpoyle and pillage, and juſtified it upon our Saviours promiſe, <hi>The meeke ſhall inherite the earth;</hi> and declared their Title was the ſame which the righteous Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites had unto the goods of the wicked Egyptians: This Story is worth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at large, and needs no application.</p>
            <p>But Wee muſt by no meanes ſay, That We have the ſame Title to Our Towne of <hi>Hull,</hi> and the Ammunition there, as any of Our Subjects have to their Lands or Money, That's <hi>A Principle that puls up the Foundation of the Liberty and Property of every Subject:</hi> Why, pray? <hi>Becauſe the Kings Property in his Townes and in his Goods, bought with the publike Money</hi> (as they conceive Our Magazine at <hi>Hull</hi> was) <hi>is inconſiſtent with the Subjects Property in their Lands, Goods, and Liberty:</hi> Doe theſe men think, That as they aſſume a power of Declaring Law (and whatſoever contradicts that Declaration, breaks their Priviledges) ſo that they have a power of declaring Senſe and Reaſon, and impoſing Logick and Syllogiſmes on the Schooles, as well as Law upon the People? Doth not all mankind know, That
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152625:4"/>ſeverall man may have ſeverall Rights and Intereſts in the ſelfe ſame Houſe and Land, and yet neither deſtroy the other? Is not the Intereſt of the Lord <hi>Paramont</hi> conſiſtent with that of the <hi>Meſme</hi> Lord, and his with that of he Tenant, and yet their Properties and Intereſts not at all confounded? And why may not Wee then have a full Lawfull Intereſt and Property in Our Town of <hi>Hull,</hi> and yet Our Subjects have a Property in their Houſes too? But We, <hi>cannot ſell or give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way at Our pleaſure Our Towns and Forts, as a private man may do his Lands or Goods:</hi> What then? Many men have no authority to Let or Set their Leaſes, or ſell their Land; have they therefore no Title to them, or Intereſt in them? May they be taken from them, becauſe they cannot ſell them? The purpoſe of Our Iourney to <hi>Hull,</hi> was, neither to ſell it, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> give it away.</p>
            <p>But for the Magazine, the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ition there, that We bought with our own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; We might ſurely have ſold that, lent, or given it away. No; <hi>We bought it with the publike Money;</hi> and the proof is, <hi>They conceive it ſo;</hi> and upon this conceit have Voted, That it ſhall be taken from Vs: Excellent Iuſtice! Suppoſe We had kept this Money by Vs, and not bought Arms with it, would they have taken it from Vs upon that conceit? Nay, may they not whereſoever this Money is (for through how many hands ſoever it hath paſſed, it is the publike Money ſtill, if it ever were) ſeize it and take it from the Owners? But the Towns, Forts, Magazine, and Kingdom is intruſted to Vs, and We are a Perſon truſted; We are ſo, God and the Law hath truſted Vs; and We have taken an Oath to diſcharge that truſt for the good and ſafety of Our people: What Oaths they have taken, We know not, unleſſe thoſe which, in this violence, they have manifeſtly, maliciouſly violated. May any thing bee taken from a man, becauſe he is truſted with it? Nay, may the perſon himſelf take away the thing he truſts, when he will, and in what manner he will? The Law hath been otherwiſe, and We beleeve will be ſo held, notwithſtanding their Declarations.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>This truſt ought to be managed by their advice, and the Kingdom hath truſted them for that purpoſe:</hi> Impoſſible! That the ſame truſt ſhould be irrevocably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Vs and our Heirs for ever, and the ſame truſt, and a power above that truſt (for ſuch is the power they pretend) be committed to others: Did not the people that ſent them, look upon them as a Body but Temporary, and diſſoluble at Our Pleaſure: And can it be beleeved, that they intended them for Our Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians and Comptrollers in the managing of that Truſt, which God and the Law hath granted to Vs and Our Poſterity for ever? What the extent of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and Truſt is, nothing can better teach them, then the Writ whereby they are met. We called them (and without that call they could not have come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) to be Our Counſellors, not Commanders; (for however they frequently confound them, the Offices are ſeverall) and Councellors, not in all things, but in ſome things; <hi>De quibuſdam arduis, &amp;c.</hi> And they will eaſily find amongſt their Preſidents, that Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (upon whoſe Time all Good Men look with Reverence) committed one <hi>Wentworth,</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Commons, to the Tower (ſitting the Houſe) but for propoſing, That they might adviſe the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152625:4"/>Queen, in a matter ſhe thought they had nothing to do to meddle in: But <hi>We are truſted:</hi> and are We the onely Perſon truſted? And may they do what their own inclination and fury leads them to? Were not they truſted by Vs, when We firſt ſent for them; and were they not truſted by Vs, when We paſſed them Our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, That We would not diſſolve them? Can it be preſumed (and preſumptions go far with them) that We truſted them with a Power to deſtroy Vs, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Our Government and Authority? If the people might be allowed to make an equitable conſtruction of the Laws and Statutes (a Doctrine avowed by them) would not all Our good Subjects ſwear, We never intended by that Act of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, that they ſhould do what they have ſince done? Were they not truſted by thoſe that have ſent them? And were they truſted to alter the Government of Church and State, and to make themſelves perpetuall Dictators over the King and People? Did they intend that the Law it ſelf ſhould be ſubject to their Votes, and that whatſoever they ſay or do, ſhould be lawfull, becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it ſo? The Oaths which they have taken, who ſent them, and without taking which, themſelves are not capable of their place in Parliament, makes the one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of giving, and the other of receiving ſuch a truſt; unleſſe they can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our good Subjects; That We are the onely ſupreme Head and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in all cauſes, and over all perſons, within Our Dominions; and yet that they have a power over Vs to conſtrain Vs to manage Our Truſt, and govern Our Power, according to their diſcretion.</p>
            <p>The Contrivers of that Declaration tell Vs, that they will never allow Vs (an humble and dutifull Expreſſion) to be Iudge of the Law; that belongs onely to them; they may, and muſt judge and declare. We all know what Power the Pope, under the Pretence of Interpreting Scriptures, and declaring Articles of Faith (though he decline the making the one or the other) hath uſurped over mens conſciences; and that under colour of having Power of Ordering all things for the good of mens Souls, he Entiles himſelf to all the Kingdoms in the World. We Will not accuſe the Framers of this Declaration (how bold ſoever they are with Vs) that they incline to Popery; of which another Maxime is, That We muſt ſubmit Our Reaſon and Vnderſtanding (and the Scripture it Self) to that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Power of his: Neither will We tell them (though they have told Vs ſo) that they uſe the very language of the Rebels of <hi>Ireland:</hi> and yet they ſay thoſe Rebels Declare, That whatſoeuer they do, is for the Good of the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doin: But Our good Subjects will eaſily put the Caſe to themſelves, Whether, if the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland</hi> in truth were, or by Art or Accident had made themſelves the Major Part of both Houſes of Parliament there, and had pretended the Truſt (in that Declaration) from the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland;</hi> thereupon had Voted their Religion and Liberty to be in danger of extirpation from a Malignant Party of Proteſtants and Puritanes; and therefore, that they ſhould put themſelves into a Poſture of defence; That the Forts and <hi>Militia</hi> of that Kingdom were to be put into the hands of ſuch perſons as they could confide in; That We were indeed truſted with the Towns, Forts, Magazines, Treaſures, Offices, and People of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152625:5"/>Kingdom, for the Good, and Safety, and beſt Advantage thereof: But as this truſt is for the uſe of the Kingdom, ſo it ought to be managed by the Adviſe of both Houſes of Parliament, whom the Kingdom had truſted for that purpoſe; it being their duty to ſee it diſcharged, according to the Condition and true Intent thereof, and by all poſſible means to prevent the contrary: We ſay, Let all Our good Subjects conſider, If that Rebellion had been plotted with this Formality, and thoſe Circumſtances, declared to be legall (at leaſt, according to the equitable ſenſe of the Law) and to be for the publike good, and juſtifiable by neceſſity (of which they were the onely Judges) Whether, though they might have thought their Deſigne the more cunning, they would beleeve it the more juſtifiable? Nay, let the Framers of this Declaration ask themſelves, If the Evil Counſellors, the Malignant Party, the Perſons Il-affected, the Popiſh Lords, and their Adherents, ſhould prove now, or hereafter to be a Major part of both Houſes (for it hath been declared a great part of both Houſes have been ſuch, and ſo might have been the greater; nay, that the greater part of the Houſe of Peers was ſuch (and We have not heard of any of their converſions) and thereupon it hath been ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly preſſed, That the Minor part of the Lords might joyn with the Major part of the Houſe of Commons) were Wee bound to conſent to all ſuch Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations as theſe men ſhould propoſe to Vs, and reſolve to bee for the publike good; and muſt the Liberty, Property, and Security of all Our Subjects, depend on what ſuch Votes ſhould declare to bee Law? Was the Order of the <hi>Militia</hi> unfit and unlawfull, whiles the Major part of the Lords refuſed to joyn in it (as they did two, if not three ſeverall times, and it was never heard, before this Parliament, that they ſhould bee ſo, and ſo often preſſed after a diſſent declared) and did it grow immediatly neceſſary for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſafety, and lawfull by the Law of the Land, as ſoon as ſo many of the diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Peeres were driven away (after their names had been required at the Bar, contrary to the Freedom and Foundation of Parliaments) that the other Opinion prevailed? Doth the Life and Liberty of the Subject depend upon ſuch Accidents of dayes and houres, that it is impoſſible for him to know his right in either? God forbid.</p>
            <p>But now to juſtifie their Invaſion of Our ancient, unqueſtioned, undoubted Right, ſetled and eſtabliſhed on Us and Our Poſterity, by God himſelf, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and ſtrengthned by all poſſible Titles of Compact, Laws, Oaths, perpetuall and uncontradicted Cuſtom by Our people: What have they alleaged, to <hi>Declare to the Kingdom</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>the Obligation that lyeth upon the Kings of this Realm to paſſe all ſuch Bills as are offered unto them by both Houſes of Parliament?</hi> (a thing never heard of till this day) An Oath (Authority enough for them to break all theirs) that is, or ought to be taken by the Kings of this Realm, which is, as well to remedy, by Law, ſuch inconveniences the Kingdom may ſuffer, as to keep and protect the Laws already in being; And the form of this Oath (they ſay) appears upon a Record there cited, and by a Clauſe in the Preamble of a Statute made in the five and twentieth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the third.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152625:5"/>
            <p>We are not enough acquainted with records, we to know whether that be fully and and ingeniouſly cited, and when, and how, and why the ſeverall clauſes have been inſerted, or taken out of the oathes formerly adminiſtred to the Kings of this Realme, yet we cannot poſſibly imagine, the aſſertion that Declaration makes; can be deduced from the words, or the matter of that oath; for unleſſe they have a power of declaring Lattin, as We as Law, ſure <hi>Eligerit</hi> ſignifieth, <hi>hath choſen</hi> (as well as <hi>Chuſe</hi>) and that it ſignifieth ſo here (beſides the authority of perpetuall practice of all ſucceeding ages (a better interpreter then their Votes) is evident by the reference it hath to cuſtomes; <hi>Conſuetudines quas vulgus elegerit,</hi> and could that be a Cuſtome, which the people ſhould chuſe after this Oath taken, and ſhould a King be ſworne to defend ſuch Cuſtomes? Beſides, can it be imagined that he ſhould bee bound by oath to paſſe ſuch Laws (and ſuch a Law is the Bill they brought to Vs of the <hi>Militia</hi>) as ſhould put the power, wherewith he is truſſed, out of himſelfe in the hands of other men, and ſo deveſt and diſable him of all poſſible power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the great buſineſſe of the oath, which is, To protect them? If we give away all Our power, or if it be taken from Vs, we cannot protect any man: And what diſcharge would it be for us, either before God or Man, (when our good Subjects, whom God and the Law hath committed to our charge, ſhall be worried and ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) to ſay, That we truſted others to protect them; that is, to doe that duty for Vs, which is eſſentially and inſeparably our owne. But that all Our good Subjects may ſee, how faithfully theſe men (who aſſume this truſt from them) deſire to diſcharge their truſt; We ſhall be contented to publiſh, for their ſatisfaction (a matter noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious enough, but which we our Selfe never thought to have been but to publiſh, and of which the Framers of that Declaration might as well have made uſe, as of a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine record they knew many of our good Subjects could not, and many of themſelves doe not underſtand) the Oath it ſelfe we tooke at our Coronation, warranted and injoyned to it by Cuſtome and directions of our Predeceſſors; and the Ceremony or their and our taking it, they may finde it in the Records of the Exchequer: This it is.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="scenario">
                        <stage>
                           <p>The Sermon being done, the Archbiſhop goeth to the King, and askes his willingneſſe to take the Oath uſually taken by his Predeceſſors.</p>
                           <p>The King ſheweth himſelfe willing, ariſeth, and goeth to the Altar; The Archbiſhop adminiſtreth theſe Queſtions, and the King anſwers them ſeverally.</p>
                        </stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Epiſcopus.</speaker>
                           <p>Sir, <hi>Will you grant and keep, and by your Oath confirme to the people of</hi> England, <hi>the Laws and Cuſtomes to them granted by the Kings of</hi> England, <hi>your Lawfull and Religious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors; and namely the Laws, Cuſtomes, and Franchiſes granted to the Clergie, by the glorious King, Saint</hi> Edward <hi>your Predeceſſor, according to the Lawes of God, the true Profeſſion of the Goſpel eſtabliſhed in this Kingdome, and agreeable to the Prerogative of the Kings thereof, and the ancient Cuſtomes of this Realme?</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>REX.</speaker>
                           <p>I grant and promiſe to keep them.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Epiſcopus.</speaker>
                           <p>Sir, <hi>Will you keep Peace and godly Agreement entirely (according to your power) both to God, the holy Church, the Clergy, and the People?</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>REX.</speaker>
                           <p>I will keep it.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:152625:6"/>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Epiſcopus.</speaker>
                           <p>Sir, <hi>Will you (to your power) cauſe Law, Juſtice, and Diſcretion in Mercy and Truth to be executed in all your Judgements?</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>REX.</speaker>
                           <p>I will.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Epiſcopus.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Will you grant, to hold and keep the Lawes and rightfull cuſtomes which the Commonalty of this your Kingdome have; and will you defend and uphold them to the honour of God, ſo much as in you lieth.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>REX.</speaker>
                           <p>I grant and promiſe ſo to doe.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <stage>Then one of the Biſhops reads this Admonition to the King before the people, with a loud voice.</stage>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Our Lord and King, We beſeech you to pardon, and to grant, and to preſerve unto us, and to the Churches committed to our charge, all Canonicall Priviledges, and due Law and Juſtice; and that you would Protect and defend us, as every good King, in his Kingdome, ought to bee Protector and Defender of the Biſhops, and the Churches under their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>The King anſwereth:</speaker>
                           <p>With a willing and devout Heart, I promiſe and grant my pardon; and that I will preſerve and maintaine to you, and the Churches committed to your charge, all Canonicall Privilenges, and due Law and Juſtice, and that I will be your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and Defender, to my power, by the aſſiſtance of God, as every good King in his Kingdome, in Right ought to protect and defend the Biſhops, and Churches under their Government.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>Then the King ariſeth, and is led to the Communion Table, where he makes a ſolemne Oath, in ſight of all the people, to obſerve the Premiſes: And laying his hand upon the Booke, ſaith:</stage>
                        <p>
                           <label>The Oath.</label> 
                           <hi>The things which I have before promiſed, I ſhall performe and keep: So helpe me God, and the Contents of this Booke.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Let all the world judge, whether ſuch Doctrine, or ſuch Concluſions as theſe Men teach, can follow, or have the leaſt pretence from this Oath.</p>
            <p>For the Preamble of the Statute, (they cite) that tels us, <hi>That the King is bound to remedy by Law, the Miſchiefes and Dammages which happen to His people;</hi> He is ſo: But is the King bound, by the Preamble of that Statute, to renounce his owne judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, His owne underſtanding, in theſe Miſchiefes, and of thoſe remedies? How farre forth He is obliged to follow the judgement of His Parliament, that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſtill confeſſeth to be a queſtion: without queſtion, none can take upon them to remedy, even miſchiefes, but by Law, for feare of greater miſchiefes then thoſe they goe about to remedy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Wee are bound in Juſtice, to conſent to their propoſalls, becauſe there is a Truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in Vs to preſerve the Kingdome, by making new Lawes:</hi> VVe are glad there is ſo; Then we are ſure no new Lawes can be made without Our conſent, and that the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe of our Anſwer, <hi>Le Roys' aviſera,</hi> if it be no denyall, is no conſent, and then the matter is not great. They will allow Vs yet <hi>A greater latitude of granting or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying, as We ſhall thinke fit, in publike Acts of Grace, as Pardons, or the like Grants of
<pb facs="tcp:152625:6"/>Favour:</hi> why doe they ſo? If thoſe Pardons and publike Acts of Grace, be for the publike good (which they may Vote they are) they will then be abſolutely in their owne diſpoſall: But have they left Vs this power? They have ſure, at leaſt, ſhared it with Vs: How elſe have they got the power to pardon Sergeant-major-Generall <hi>Skippon</hi> (a new Officer, of State, and a Subject, we have no authority to ſent to ſpeak with) and all other perſons imployed by them, and ſuch as have imployed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for them, not onely for what they have done, but for what they ſhall doe? If they have power to declare ſuch Actions to be no Treaſon, which we would not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and ſuch Actions to be Treaſon, which needs no pardon, the Latitude they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Vs, of granting or denying of Pardons, is a Jewell they may ſtill be contented to ſuffer Vs to weare in our Crowne, and never thinke themſelves the more in danger.</p>
            <p>All this conſidered; The Contriver of that Meſſage (ſince they will afford him no better Title) whom they are angry with, doth not conceive the people of this Land to be ſo void of common ſenſe, as to beleeve Vs (who have denyed no one thing for the eaſe and benefit of them, which in Juſtice or Prudence could be asked; or in honour and conſcience could be granted) to have caſt off all care of our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects good; and the Framers and Deviſers of that Declaration (who have endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to render us odious to our Subjects, and them diſloyall to us, by pretending ſuch a truſt from them) to have onely taken it up: Neither (we are confident) will they be ſatisfied, when they feele the miſery and the Burthens, which the fury and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of thoſe people will bring upon them, with being told that Calamity proceeds from evill Councellors, whom no body can name; from Plots and Conſpiracies, which no man can diſcover; and from Feares and Jealouſies, which no man under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands: And therefore, that the conſideration of it, be left to the Conſcience, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Affection, and Loyalty of Our good Subjects, who doe underſtand the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdome, we are well content.</p>
            <p>Where will the folly and madneſſe of theſe people end? who would have our people beleeve, that our abſenting our ſelf from <hi>London</hi> (where, with our ſafety, we could not ſtay) and the continuing Our Magazine at <hi>Hull,</hi> proceeds from the ſecret plots of the Papiſts here, and to advance the deſignes of the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland:</hi> But it is no wonder, that they, who can beleeve Sir <hi>Iohn Hothams</hi> ſhutting us out of <hi>Hull</hi> to be an act of affection and loyalty, will beleeve that the Papiſts, or the Turks, perſwaded us to go thither.</p>
            <p>An (can any ſober man think that Declaration to be the conſent of either, or both Houſes of Parliament, unaltered either by Fraud or Force, which (after ſo many Thanks and humble Acknowledgement of our gratious favour in our Meſſage of the 20. of January ſo often and unanimouſly preſented unto us from both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (tells us that the Meſſage at firſt was, and (as often as it hath been ſince mentioned by us) hath been a breach of Priviledge (of which they have not uſed to be ſo negligent, as in four moneths not to complain, if ſuch a breach had been) and that the way and method of proceeding ſhould not be propoſed to them, as if we had onely authority to call them together, none to tell them what they were to do, not ſo much as with reference to our own affairs: what their own Method hath been, and whither it hath led them, and brought the Kingdom, all men ſee; what ours would have been, if ſeaſonably and timely applied unto, let all men judge. We will ſpeak no more of it.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152625:7"/>
            <p>But ſee now what excellent Inſtances they have found out to prove an Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if not in Vs, in ſome about Vs, to civill warre: <hi>Their gving with Vs to the Houſe of Commons</hi> (ſo often urged, and ſo fully anſwered) <hi>Their attending on Vs to</hi> Hampton Court; <hi>and appearing in a warlike manner at</hi> Kingſton <hi>upon</hi> Thames; <hi>Our going to</hi> Hull; <hi>Their drawing their Swords at</hi> York, <hi>demanding, Who world be for the King; the declaring Sir</hi> Iohn Hotham <hi>Traitor, before the Meſſage ſent to the Parliament; the Propoſitions to the Gentry in Yorkſhire, to aſsiſt Vs againſt him, before We had received an anſwer from the Parliament:</hi> All deſperate Inſtances of an Inclination to a civill warre; Examine them againe: The manner and intent of Our going to the Houſe of Commons, Wee ſet forth at large in Our Anſwer to their Declaration of the nineteenth of May; let all men judge. Next, Doe theſe men themſelves beleive (to what purpoſe ſoever that Rumour hath ſerved their turns) that there was an Apparence in warlike man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames?</hi> Doe they not know, that whenſoever Wee have been at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> ſince Our firſt comming to the Crowne, there was never a leſſe Apparence, or in a leſſe warlike manner then at the time they meane: Wee ſhall ſay no more, But that Our Apparence, in a warlike manner, at <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> and theirs at <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Hull,</hi> is very different. What is meant by the drawing of ſwords at <hi>York,</hi> and demanding, who would be for the King, muſt bee inquired at <hi>London,</hi> for We believe very few in <hi>York</hi> underſtand the meaning of it. For Our going to <hi>Hull</hi> (which they will by no meanes endure ſhall be called a Viſit) whether it were not the way to prevent, rather then to make a Civill Warre, is very obvious: And the declaring him a Traitor, in the very Act of his Treaſon, will never be thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable, but by thoſe, who believe him to be a loving and loyall Subject; no more then the endeavouring to make the Gentlemen of this County ſenſible of that Treaſon (which they are, in an honourable and dutifull degree) before We received Our Anſwer from both Houſes of Parliament: For if they had been (as We expected they ſhould have been) ſenſible of that intollerable injury offered to Vs; might not We have had occaſion to have uſed the affection of theſe Gentleman? Were we ſure that Sir <hi>John Hotham,</hi> who had kept Vs out, without their Order (Wee ſpeake of a publike Order) would have let Vs in when they had bidden him? And if they had not ſuch a ſenſe of Vs (as the Caſe falls out to be) had We not more reaſon to make Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to thoſe Gentlemen, whoſe readineſſe and affection We, or Our Poſterity, ſhall never forget?</p>
            <p>But this buſineſſe of <hi>Hull</hi> ſticks ſtill with them, and finding Our Queſtions hard, they are pleaſed to Anſwer Vs by asking Vs other Queſtions: No matter for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> (which have beene ſo often urged, as one of their principall Grounds of their Feares and Iealouſies, and which drew that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion from us) they aske Vs, <hi>Why, ſince We held it neceſſary that a Governour ſhould bee placed in</hi> Hull, <hi>Sir</hi> Iohn Hotham <hi>ſhould be refuſed by Vs, and the Earle of</hi> Newcaſtle <hi>ſent downe?</hi> We anſwer, Becauſe we had a better Opinion of the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> then of Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham,</hi> and deſired to have ſuch a Governour over Our Townes, (if Wee muſt have any) as ſhould keep them for, and not againſt Vs: And if his going downe were in a more private way, then Sir <hi>John Hothams,</hi> it was becauſe We had that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to make a noyſe, by Leavying and Billetting of Souldiers in a peaceable Time, upon Our good Subjects, as it ſeems Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> carried downe with him: And the Imputation which is caſt by the way upon that Earle, to make his Reputation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:152625:7"/>
               <hi>thought was not Ground enough for a Judiciall Proceeding,</hi> (it is wonder it was not) <hi>was yet Ground enough of Suſpition,</hi> muſt be the Caſe of every Subject in <hi>England</hi> (and we wiſh it went no higher:) If every vile Aſpertion contrived by unknowne hands, upon unknown or unimaginable Grounds (which is the way practiſed to bring any vertuous and deſerving men into obloquy) ſhall receive the leaſt credit or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance in the world.</p>
            <p>They tell us their Exception to thoſe Gentlemen, who delivered their Petition to to us at <hi>York,</hi> was, <hi>That they preſumed to take the ſtile upon them of all the Gentry and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that County, whereas</hi> (they ſay) <hi>ſo many more of as good Quality as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, of that County, were of another opinion; and have ſince, by their Petition to Vs, diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed that Act:</hi> Their Information, in that point, is no better then it uſeth to be, and and they will find, that neither the number, or the quality of thoſe who have, or will diſavow that Petition, are as they imagine; though too many weak perſons are miſſed (which they doe, and will every day more underſtand) by the Faction, Skill, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of that true <hi>Malignant Party,</hi> of which wee doe, and have reaſon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine: They ſay, they <hi>Have received no Petition of ſo ſtrange a nature;</hi> what nature? <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Votes of both Houſes:</hi> that is, they have received no Petition they had no mind to receive: But we told them, and we tell them againe, and all our good Subjects will tell them, that they have received Petitions (with joy and approbation) againſt the votes of both Houſes of their Predeceſſors, confirmed and eſtabliſhed into Lawes, by the conſent of Vs and our Anceſtors, and allowed thoſe Petitions to carry the Stile, and to ſeem to carry the deſires o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cities, Townes, and Counties, when of either Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Towne, or County very few knowne or conſiderable perſons have been privy to ſuch Petitions: whereas, in truth, the Petitions delivered to Vs (againſt which they except) carried not the Stile of All, but Some of the Gentry and Inhabitants, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed no other conſent, then ſuch as went viſibly along with it.</p>
            <p>But we are all this while in a miſtake <hi>The Magazine at</hi> Hull <hi>is not taken from us:</hi> Who told you ſo? They who aſſure you (and whom, without breaking their privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, you muſt believe) that Sir <hi>Lo: Hothams</hi> ſhutting the gates againſt us, and reſiſting our entrance with armed men (though we thought it in defiance of us) <hi>was indeed in obedience to us and our Authority, and for our Service, and the Service of the Kingdome. He was to let none in, but ſuch as came with our Authority, ſignified by both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (himſelfe and they had ordered it ſo) <hi>and therefore he kept us out, onely till We, or he might ſend for their directions.</hi> We know not whether the Contrivers of that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration meant that our good Subjects ſhould ſo ſoone underſtand (though it was plain enough to be underſtood) the meaning of the Kings authority, ſignified by both ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſes of Parliament: But ſure the world will now eaſily diſcerne, in what mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable caſe we had, by this time, been ('tis bad enough as it is) if we had conſented to their Bill, or to their Ordinance of the <hi>Mili ia,</hi> and given thoſe men power to have raiſed all the Armes of the Kingdome againſt us (for the common good) by our owne Authority: would they not (as they have kept us from <hi>Hull</hi>) by this time have beaten us from <hi>York</hi> and purſued us out of the Kingdome, in our owne behalfe? Nay, may not this Munition <hi>(which is not taken from us)</hi> be imployed againſt us? Nor againſt our Authority, ſignified by both Houſes of Parliament, but onely to kill thoſe ill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, the <hi>Malignant Party,</hi> which is about us; and yet for our good, for the publike good (they will declare it ſo) and ſo no Treaſon within the Statute of 25. of <hi>Ed.</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> hath left us (<hi>the King of</hi> England) abſolutely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:152625:8"/>leſſe provided for, in point of ſafety, then the meaneſt Subjeſt of the Kingdome; and every Subject of this Land (for whoſe ſecurity that Law was made, that they may know their duty, and their danger in breaking it) may bee made a Traytor, when theſe men pleaſe to ſay, He is ſo: But doe they think, that upon ſuch an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation (upon pretence of Authority of Book-Caſes, and Preſidents, which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, they would have cited, if they had been to their purpoſe) out of which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can reſult, but confuſion to King and people; will find any credit with our good Subjects? and that ſo excellent a Law made both for ſecurity of King and people) ſhall be ſo eluded, By an Interpretation, no learned Lawyer in <hi>England</hi> will at this houre (We believe) ſet under his hand, notwithſtanding the Authority of that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, which, wee hope, ſhall bring nothing but infamy upon the Contrivers of it.</p>
            <p>Now to their priviledges: Though it be true they ſay, <hi>That their priviledges doe not extend to Treaſon, Felony, or breach of the Peace, ſo as to attempt Members from all manner of Proces and Triall, yet it doth priviledge them in the way or method of their Triall; the Cauſe muſt be firſt brought before them, and their Conſent asked before you can proceed:</hi> Why then their priviledges extend as farre in theſe caſes, as in any that are moſt unqueſtioned; for no priviledge whatſoever, exempts them from all manner of Proces and Triall, if you firſt acquaint the Houſe with it, and they give you leave to proceed by thoſe Proces, or to that Triall: But, by this Rule, if a Member of either Houſe commit a Murther, you muſt, by no meanes, meddle with him, till you have acquainted that Houſe (of which he is a Member) and received their direction for your proceeding; aſſuring your ſelfe, He will not ſtirre from that place where you left him, till you returne with their conſent: <hi>Should it be otherwiſe, it would be in the power of every man, under pretence of Murther, to take one after another, and as many as he pleaſeth, and ſo conſequently bring a Parliament to what he pleaſeth, when he pleaſeth:</hi> If a Member of either Houſe ſhall take a Purſe at <hi>Yorke</hi> (he may as probably take a Purſe from a Subject, as Armes againſt his King) you muſt ride to <hi>London</hi> to know what to doe, and he may ride with you, and take a new Purſe every Stage, and muſt not be apprehended, or declared a Felon, till you have asked that Houſe, of which he is a Member: <hi>Should it be otherwiſe, it might be in every mans power, to accuſe as many Members as he would, of taking Purſes, and ſo bring a Parliament (and ſo all Parliament,) to nothing.</hi> Would theſe men be beleeved? And yet they make no doubt <hi>But every one who hath taken the Proteſtation, will defend this Doctrine with his Life and Fortune.</hi> Will not Our Subjects beleeve, That they have impoſed a pretty Proteſtation upon them, and that they had a very good end in the doing it, if it obligeth them to ſuch hazards, to ſuch undertakings? Muſt they forget or neglect Our Perſon, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Eſtate, which by that Proteſtation they are bound to defend, and in ſome degree do underſtand; and muſt they onely venture their Lives and Fortunes, to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie Priviledges they know not, or ever heard of before? Or are they bound, by that Proteſtation, to beleeve, That the Framers of that Declaration, have power to extend their owne Priviledges, as farre as they think fit, and to contract Our Rights as much as they pleaſe, and that they are bound to beleeve them in either, and to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture their Lives and Fortunes in that quarrell?</p>
            <p>From Declaring how meane a perſon we are, and how much the Kingdom hath been miſtaken in the underdanding of the <hi>Statute</hi> of 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. concerning Treaſon; and that all men need not fear leavying War againſt us, ſo they have their order to
<pb facs="tcp:152625:8"/>warrant them; they proceed, in the ſpirit of declaring, to certifie our Subjects in the miſtakings, which neer one hundred and fiftie years have been received, concerning the <hi>Statue</hi> of the eleventh year of <hi>H.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. (a Stature our good Subjects will read with comfort) and tell them, that the ſerving of the King, for the time being, cannot be meant of <hi>Perkin Warbeck,</hi> or of any that ſhould call himſelf King, but <hi>Such a one as is allowed and received by the Parliament in the behalf of the Kingdom;</hi> And are we not ſo allowed? However through a dark miſt of words, and urging their old Priviledges (which we hope we have ſufficiently anſwered, and will be every day more confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the actions of our good Subjects) they conclude, <hi>That thoſe that ſhall guide themſelves by the judgement of Parliament</hi> (which they ſay is their own) ought, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever happen, to be ſecure and free from all all account and penalties, upon the ground and equity of that very Statute. How far their own Chancellors may help them in that equitie, We know not, but (by the help of God, and that good Law) we ſhall allow no ſuch equitie.</p>
            <p>So then, here is the Doctrine of that Declaration, and theſe are the Poſitions of the Contrivers of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That they have an abſolute power of declaring the Law, and that what ſoever they declare to be ſo, ought not to be queſtioned by our ſelf, or any Subject: ſo that all Right and ſafety of us and our people muſt depend upon their pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That no Preſidents can be limits to bound their proceedings: ſo they may do what they pleaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That a Parliament may diſpoſe of any thing, wherein the King or Subject hath a right, for the publike good; That they, without the King, are this Parliament, and Iudge of this publike good; and that our conſent is not neceſſary: ſo, the life, and libertie of the Subject, and all the good Laws made for the ſecurity of them, may be diſpoſed of, and repealed by the major part of both Houſes, at any time preſent, and by any wayes and means procured ſo to be; and we have no power to protect them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no Member of either Houſe, ought to be troubled or medled with, for Treaſon, Felony, or any other crime, without the cauſe firſt brought before them, that they may judge of the fact, and their leave obtained to proceed.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the ſoeveraigne power reſides in both Houſes of Parliament, and that we have no negative voyce: ſo then we our ſelf muſt be ſubject to their commands.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the leavying of forces againſt te perſonall commands of the King (though accompanied with his preſence) is not leavying war againſt the King; but the leavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing war againſt his Laws and authority (which they have power to declare and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie) though not againſt his perſon, is leavying war againſt the King; and that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot be committed againſt his perſon, otherwiſe then as he is intruſted with the Kingdom, and diſcharging that truſt, and that they have a power to judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he diſcharge this truſt or no.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That, <hi>If they ſhould makethe higheſt Preſidents of other Parliaments, their Patitions there would he no cauſe to complain of want of modeſty or Duty in them:</hi> That is, They may Depoſe us when they will, and are not to be blamed for ſo doing.</p>
            <p>And now (as if the meer publiſhing of their Reſolutions, would not onely prevail with the people, but, in the inſtant, deſtroy all ſpirit and courage in us, to preſerve our own right and honour) they have, ſince, taken the boldneſſe to aſſault us with certain Propoſitions, which they call, <hi>The moſt neceſſary effectuall means for the removing
<pb facs="tcp:152625:9"/>thoſe Iealouſies and Differences between us and our People:</hi> That is, that we will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to direſt our ſelf of all our Regall Rights and Dignities; be content with the Title of a King and ſuffer them (according to their Diſcretion) to govern us and the Kingdom, and to diſpoſe of our Children: how ſuteable and agreeable this Doctrine, and theſe Demands are, to the affection of our loving Subjects, under whoſe Truſt theſe men pretend to ſay and do theſe monſtrous things, and to deſigne, not onely the ruine of our Perſon, but of Monarchy it ſelf (which we may juſtly ſay, is more then ever was offered in any of our predeceſſors times; for though the Perſon of the King hath been ſometimes unjuſtly depoſed, yet the Regall power was never, before this time, ſtrucken at) we beleeve our good Subjects will finde ſome way to let them and the World know: and from this time ſuch who have been miſ-led by their ill Counſels, to have any hand in the execution of the <hi>Militia,</hi> will ſee to what ends their Service is deſigned; and therefore if they ſhall preſume hereafter to meddle in it, they muſt expect, that we will immediately proceed againſt them as actuall rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of ſedition, and as enemies to our ſoveraign power.</p>
            <p>We hane done: and ſhall now expect the worſt actions theſe men have power to commit againſt us: (worſe words they cannot give us) and we doubt not, but the major part of both Houſes of Parliament, when they may come together with their honour and ſafety, (as well thoſe who were ſurpriſed, at the paſſing of it, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not the Malice in it, and the confuſion that muſt grow by it, if beleeved, as thoſe who were abſent or involved) will ſo far reſent the Indignitie offered to us, the diſhonour to themſelves, and the miſchief to the whole Kingdom, by that Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they will ſpeedily make the foul Contrivers of it, inſtances of their exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarie Iuſtice, and brand them and their Doctrine with the Marks of their perpetuall Scorn and Indignation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
